<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Articles of the giuing ouer of the large, ample, and imperiall cittie of Groning also the Articles and conditions, whervpon His Highnes, and the Honorable William Ludowick, Earle of Nassow, at this present, with the aduice of the counsell of the Estates of the Vnited Prouinces, are content to agree vnto, for reducing and reconciliation of the    said cittie of Groning : likewise the agreement, concluded between His Highnes, and the chiefe lieutenant Laukema, with the captaines, commaunders, and common  souldiours, beeing in garrison within the fore-sayd cittie / doone the xxi. and xxii. of July, 1594 ; with repetition ofthe besieging of the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12392.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24514069</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24514069</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27749</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27749)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1852:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Articles of the giuing ouer of the large, ample, and imperiall cittie of Groning also the Articles and conditions, whervpon His Highnes, and the Honorable William Ludowick, Earle of Nassow, at this present, with the aduice of the counsell of the Estates of the Vnited Prouinces, are content to agree vnto, for reducing and reconciliation of the    said cittie of Groning : likewise the agreement, concluded between His Highnes, and the chiefe lieutenant Laukema, with the captaines, commaunders, and common  souldiours, beeing in garrison within the fore-sayd cittie / doone the xxi. and xxii. of July, 1594 ; with repetition ofthe besieging of the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn VVoolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1594]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First part is translation of: De articulen vant overgheuen der wijdtvermaerde keyserlijcke stercke stadt Groeninghen.</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains illustration.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks all after signature A₄.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Groningen (Netherlands) --  History --  Siege, 1594.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27749:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27749:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Articles of the giuing ouer of the large, ample, and imperiall Cittie of <hi>GRONING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Articles and conditions, whervpon his Highnes, and the honorable <hi>William Ludowick</hi> Earle of <hi>Naſſow,</hi> at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, with the aduice of the Counſell of the Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces, are content to agree vnto: for reducing and reconciliation of the Citty, Cittizens, and Indwellers of the ſaid Cittie of <hi>Groning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe the agreement, concluded between his Highnes, and the chiefe Lieutenant <hi>Laukema,</hi> with the Captaines, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders, and common Souldiours, beeing in Garriſon within the fore-ſayd Cittie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doone the xxi. and xxii. of July, 1594. With repetition of the beſieging of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the capture of Groningen</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Iohn VVoolfe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_surrender">
            <pb facs="tcp:27749:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27749:2"/>
            <head>¶The Articles of the giuing ouer of the imperiall Cittie of <hi>Groning.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE excellent Prince and Lorde <hi>Morrice</hi> of <hi>Naſſow, &amp;c.</hi> hauing reſcued <hi>Coeuerden,</hi> where the common Enemie with all his power on foote and on horſebacke, had lyne al the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſtrengthened himſelfe with ſundrie Trenches, againſt the inſurrection of our people, hath not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding not tarryed the comming of our Campe, but hath left the Caſtle of <hi>Coeuerden,</hi> with all her Trenches and Campes.</p>
            <p>Which done, his Highnes came before <hi>Groning,</hi> the 20. of May, viewed the Cittie, and ſummoned it. Their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere was, that they ſhould firſt lye a yeere &amp; a day before it, and then ſhoulde ſummon the ſame. There ſhoulde you haue ſéene many kindes of cariages, in very great quantitie, of rafters, poſtes, Deales, plancks and boords, where-with many Ships were laden. There was tenne Ships ſent from <hi>Gorcum</hi> with boordes, beſides many hundreds which came from <hi>Swoll</hi> and other places, and were beſpoken.</p>
            <p>There came to the Campe before <hi>Groning,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my Lords the States, vnder the conduct of his Highnes, about one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fortie Enſignes of footemen: as high Dutch, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, Scots, Netherlanders, and Fréeſlanders. The Freeſlanders vnder the conduct of <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Naſſow.</hi> There was viij. Enſignes preſently ſent before the Forte at <hi>Aurikeizill,</hi> to take in the ſame: for they held out ſtoutly, and attended for fiue Enſignes, that came with bridges &amp; Ladders for the aſſault.</p>
            <p>And ſtanding readie to employ all their might thereon, there came three other Enſignes from the other ſide, with bridges, many bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dles of Bulruſhes bound together in ſacks, pitched and nayled vnder Tables made of Deale-bords, ouer which they ranne to the wall of the Fort. They which had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27749:3"/> no Ladders, did ſticke their daggers in, and climed vp by them. The people ſéeing that they were ouer-fallen, cryed for grace, but it was too late: for they had ſpoken very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious words to the Dromſter, wherefore they were all ouer-come, and of one hundred and thirty, there was not fiue left aliue. Which was no ſmall feare to them of <hi>Groning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as alſo the driuing out of their folke out of the Trenche at <hi>Hogherbrug.</hi> So that they of <hi>Groning,</hi> were conſtrained to driue their Cattell vnder the Towne wall, where they could not all be kept, but ſome were fedde with Hay in the Cittie. There was about foure-ſcore of thoſe without, which were taken by our men.</p>
            <p>After this, they iſſued forth of the Citty in ſundry places vpon our men, with the helpe of fiue Enſignes of Souldiers, that lay in <hi>Shutendiepe,</hi> which place is ſtrongly defended ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally from the Citty, lying vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water called the <hi>Vaert<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>) which the Coronell made at that time. With this their iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, they did our folkes very much harme. But after we had made our Trenches, digged our Lope-ditches, &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened the ſame, their left they of their iſſuing out.</p>
            <p>Great was the carefulnes of his Highnes and my Lords the States, in the fortifying and making ſure of our Campe, towards all quarters, where any feare was of aſſaulting. And then employing all their force againſt the Citty, with dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and placing of their Ordinance. Yea, in thrée places they came to their very wall, ſo that in two places, they digged and vndermined twenty and thirtie foote within their Wall. They within reſted not, but defended themſelues: inſomuch that through their manifold ſhooting, there was founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue two thouſand pellets.</p>
            <p>Heereby is to be coniectured, that they ſhotte foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſhotte at the leaſt, with great Ordinaunce. For at the beginning they were prouided with foure hundred Barrells of powder, which were leſſned to fiftie, and yet were not they of the beſt.</p>
            <p>Vppon the Gate called the <hi>Herren Port,</hi> were eight great peeces placed, and wholie ſhot of. There were many houſes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27749:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhaken, and ſpoyled with the Ordinance, and ſomtimes with fire-works out of the Campe, and balles of wild-fire, which in ſunder places did ſette theyr houſes on fire: where-vppon preſently followed pellets of ſtone, and hayle-ſhot mingled with wild-fire. Whereby the hearts of the Cittizens began heere and there to faint, and were brought to ſuch point, that they tooke pledges one of another.</p>
            <p>The Rulers were brought to ſuch extremety, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauiate the matter, (not ſo much through the beſieging, but by certaine Souldiers of <hi>Sluiten-deepe,</hi> which were let into the Citty,) that they were forced to hold their handes, which made a rumor in the Citty, inſomuch that ſome loſt theyr lyues by it. Thys being ſtilled and pacified, the Souldiours had afterwards no good reſt or quietnes for want of ſleepe, by reaſon of theyr continuall watching. The chiefe of them was occaſion heereby to write to <hi>Don Verdugo,</hi> for a ſupply of Souldiours, munition, and money. One of the carryers of theſe Letters was ſlaine, and hanged vp againſt the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: the other was pardoned, becauſe hee bewrayed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the Citty.</p>
            <p>Vpon the Roundell (which was made long agoe, and in the time of Duke <hi>Daline,</hi> called <hi>The Caſtle,</hi>) were alſo eyght great péeces of Ordinance planted, one of the corners wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was wholy ſhotte downe, and ſo made vnfenceable. His Highnes through his diligence and endeuour going heere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſee the manner, a ſhotte light vpon his Trench, that thoſe which ſtoode harde by him, were thereby ſprinckled in their faces.</p>
            <p>One of the three mynes vnder the ſayde Roundell, named <hi>Rauelin,</hi> was digged, which beeing perceiued by them of the Citty, was countermined, by which our men entred, placing of their powder, and alarme preſently giuen. Whilſt they of the Citty were ſetting of their watch at the ſaide <hi>Rauelin,</hi> the powder was by a traine ſuddainly ſet on fire, with ſuch thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering noyſe and duſt, that for the ſpace of three houres, one man coulde not ſée another. The chiefeſt Lieutenant was alſo ſlayne.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:27749:4"/>
            <p>The Reader may well thinke, howe armes, legges and and whole bodies of men, were blowne away in the ayre, for two of them fell into our Trenches, wherof one was yet aliue. Thys Bulwarke brake and fell downe, according as we wiſhed, and hath made a braue bancke. Alſo the way fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp betweene <hi>Rauelin</hi> and the Cittie, our men crept in, without loſing of any one man: where they founde ſixe pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordinance, and certaine men wrapped vp in the earth, which were yet aliue. The ſame day in the Euening in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our watch, we loſt eyght Souldiours.</p>
            <p>They in the Cittie ſeeing this, were at their wits end, as if the day of Iudgement had beene come. Straightwaies <hi>Iohn den Boer,</hi> or <hi>Iohn the Clowne,</hi> was ſent out with a Taber and a pype, yet that day all was not ended. But the next day, they of the Cittie, vpon good aſſurance and promiſe of his Highnes, came forth in foure ſeuerall companies, that is to ſay, the Clergie, the Magiſtrates, the chiefeſt of the Souldiours, and the men of Occupations. One of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would not truſt another. Heerevpon his Highnes ſaid vnto them, Looke what you agree to, is wholie giuen you through my liberalitie: for I count my ſelfe aſſured of the Citty. In the end, after many debatings, the xxij. day of Iulie, theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles following were agreed vpon.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, that his Highneſſe for the firſt time, may diſplace the Magiſtrate, and place him again, and the ſworne Communaltie, at his pleaſure.</item>
               <item>2. That the Gildes or Companies ſhall in that reſpect, be ſet a ſide, that they ſhall haue nothing to ſay in the policie of the Cittie. But the Counſell ſhall deale therein with the ſworne Communaltie, ſuch as the Counſell will vſe therevnto.</item>
               <item>3. That his Highnes may put Souldiours into the Cittie at his pleaſure: but yet in ſuch manner as is vſed in Freeſland.</item>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27749:4"/>
               <item>4. That the Cittie ſhall renounce the King, and declare him their enemie. And alſo bee ſeaſed with Impoſts or any others, as the Citties in Freeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</item>
               <item>5. That no other Religion be ſuffered, but onlie the true reformed Religion.</item>
               <item>6. That during theſe warres, his Highnes ſhal yeerely chooſe out fiue of the ſworne Communalty, which ſhall appoynt the Counſell.</item>
               <item>7. That the Garriſon of the Enemie ſhall paſſe ouer the <hi>Rhine,</hi> leauing their Enſignes behind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſwearing in thrée moneths not to ſerue on this ſide the ſame.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But his Highnes afterwards, at the interceſſion of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Gentlemen, bid the Enſignes to be giuen them at their departing.</p>
            <p>Touching all other Articles, the ſame ſhall remaine at the diſpoſition of the generall Eſtates. The Lord giue his Highnes long life, that thereby all they may be forced which exerciſe Spaniſh tyrannie, and oppreſſe the good.</p>
            <p>Almightie GOD be thanked for his grace and fauour, and thys great victorie, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
